{"tossups": [{"question": "The MS<em> Alfhem</em> helped this country bypass a US-led arms blockade by bringing Czechoslovakian weapons. A general from this country managed to capture a flag from William Walker\u2019s house unharmed. Guerilla fighters were opposed in the \u201cguns and beans\u201d campaign implemented by its former president Efrain Rios Montt. Operation PBSUCCESS overthrew President Jacobo Arbenz of this country on behalf of the United Fruit Company. For the point, name this Central American country now led by Jimmy Morales.", "answer": "<b> Guatemala</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2013, 18 people were killed in massive flooding on this island caused by Cyclone Cleopatra. The Treaty of The Hague granted control of this island to a royal house that ruled from Turin until Napoleon forced them off the mainland and south of the Strait of Bonafacio. The House of Savoy ruled this island in an alliance with Piedmont until Victor Emmanuel II, its king, completed the Risorgimento. Cagliari is the capital city of, for the point, what Mediterranean island that lies south of Corsica?", "answer": "<b> Sardinia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The arrival of French ships at Tybee Island near this city forced a withdrawal by John Maitland. This city was captured by Archibald Campbell in the Revolutionary War, and Casimir Pulaski died during a failed retake of this city. Joseph Wheeler\u2019s cavalry harassed a force that captured this city, along with 25,000 bales of cotton and 150 guns. For the point, name this \u201cChristmas present\u201d to Abraham Lincoln at the end of the Sherman\u2019s March to the Sea in Georgia.", "answer": "<b> Savannah</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Gurkha units are heavily associated with this country. For the point, a massive April 2015 earthquake struck what Himalayan country with capital at Kathmandu?", "answer": "<b> Nepal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event was compared to \u201can entomologist killing a beetle on a pin\u201d by one of its perpetrators. This event involved a murder committed with a chisel, after which the victim was dumped at Wolf Lake. Its perpetrators pled guilty, but were spared the death penalty after a 12-hour speech by their lawyer, Clarence Darrow, who argued that Nietzsche\u2019s writings were to blame. For the point, name this 1924\u201cTrial of the Century\u201d in which the murderers of Bobby Franks, two University of Chicago students, were sentenced to life in prison.", "answer": "the<b> Leopold and Loeb</b> murder case (accept any answer naming both Nathan Freudenthal <b>Leopold</b>, Jr.<b> and</b> Richard Albert<b> Loeb</b>, including their crime or the ensuing trial; accept the<b> murder of</b> Bobby<b> Franks</b> before his name is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Andrew Hacker\u2019s<em> The Math Myth</em> notes that, in 2004, Jeb Bush incorrectly answered a question about one of these figures whose correct answers included 36.9 and 53.1 degrees. In 1876, James Garfield used three of these figures to construct a trapezoid. In the aforementioned anecdote, Jeb Bush did correctly note that \u201c90\u201d and \u201cwhatever remains on 180\u201d would be two of its angles. For the point, name this type of polygon whose side lengths follow the Pythagorean formula.", "answer": "<b> right triangle</b> (prompt on triangle)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "When commissioned as a war artist, this man painted wounded soldiers walking to a dressing station. Earlier, this artist included two guitars hanging on the wall of a room in which a gypsy dances<em> El Jaleo</em> [hah-LAY-oh]. He is also known for intimate portraits, such as one of two girls hanging paper lanterns. In another work, this artist of<em> Carnation, Lily, Lily, Rose</em> contrasted the pale skin and black satin dress of its subject, Virginie Gautreau [vir-zhih-NEE goh-TROH]. For the point, name this painter of<em> Madame X</em>.", "answer": "John Singer<b> Sargent</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One of this polity\u2019s colonies rebelled in the Revolt of St. Titus, and it feuded over Comacchio with Ercole [AIR-koh-lay] I of Ferrara in the Salt War. The Kingdom of Negroponte was a colony of this city, which was targeted by an alliance between Louis XII of France and Pope Julius II, resulting in the War of the League of Cambrai. The Arsenale, a massive shipyard, was built in, for the point, what \u201cMost Serene Republic,\u201d an Italian city with many canals?", "answer": "<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In honor of the defending champion, the late Payne Stewart, the 2000 iteration of this event began with a 21-drive salute into the Pacific Ocean; that iteration of this event was the most lopsided in its history, with a champion at 12-under and runner-up at 3-over. Phil Mickelson has finished second in this event six times, including at Bethpage Black twice. Jordan Spieth followed his 2015 Masters championship two months later by winning this event, whose final round is traditionally played on Father\u2019s Day. For the point, name this major golf tournament that precedes the British Open and PGA Championship.", "answer": "<b> U.S. Open</b> (prompt on the Open)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "In this work, one character teaches Mozart\u2019s Clarinet Concerto to a group of Chinese soldiers, while another character remembers hearing a clucking chicken that was actually a crying child. This work was five times the standard length for its series, was officially titled \u201cGoodbye, Farewell, and Amen,\u201d and ends as Hawkeye\u2019s helicopter takes him away from the Korean War. For the point, name this 1983 television event, which still holds the record for most-watched TV series finale.", "answer": "<b> M*A*S*H</b> series<b> finale</b> (accept descriptions; accept<b> M*A*S*H</b> alone once \u201cseries finale\u201d is read; prompt on other partial answers; accept<b> Goodbye, Farewell, and Amen</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The 1991 Bitesse Accords were violated by UNITA\u2019s sale of these items, and a specific UN ban on these items was encouraged by the research of Robert Fowler. Charles Taylor was accused of dealing these items with the RUF. Unlike variants found in the DRC and Sierra Leone, Zimbabwean examples of this item are considered to be approved by the Kimberley Process, which curtails the flow of these items into the mainstream jewelry industry. For the point, give this term for controversial gems whose sales fund warlords in Africa.", "answer": "<b> blood diamond</b>s (or<b> conflict diamond</b>s; accept descriptions; prompt on diamonds; prompt on general terms like gems before \u201cjewelry\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In a \u201cFragment of a Turkish Tale\u201d by this writer, the title infidel become a vampire. This poet of \u201cThe Giaour\u201d [JOW-er] also used the story of Genevan patriot Fran\u00b8cois Bonivard [fran-SWAH boh-nee-VAR] as the basis for \u201cThe Prisoner of Chillon\u201d [shee-YOHN]. Another of his poems praises a \u201cmind at peace with all below.\u201d This poet affixed a sarcastic dedication to \u201cBob\u201d Southey [SOW-thee] to an \u201cepic satire\u201dabout the title renowned lover. For the point, name this Romantic poet of \u201cShe Walks in Beauty\u201d and <em>Don Juan</em> [JEW-un] who died in the Greek War of Independence.", "answer": "George<b> Gordon</b>, Lord<b> Byron</b> (accept either underlined name)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This composer was inspired by footage of World War II to write his<em> Symphony in Three Movements</em>. For the 35th anniversary of Tchaikovsky\u2019s death, he wrote the ballet<em> The Fairy\u2019s Kiss</em>. He included\u201cMystic Circles of Young Girls\u201d in a work that opens with a high bassoon solo. Ivan breaks Kashchei\u2019s [ka-SHE\u2019s] magic egg in this composer\u2019s first collaboration with Sergei Diaghilev\u2019s [dee-ah-guh-lev\u2019s] Ballets Russes [ballet roose]. For the point, name this composer of<em> Petrushka</em> and<em> The Firebird</em>.", "answer": "Igor<b> Stravinsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man once noted \u201cit is just as easy to believe the miracle of Jonah as any other miracle in the Bible.\u201d This man argued that \u201cman is essentially devout\u201d in his \u201cPrince of Peace\u201d speech, given at many Chautauqua gatherings in 1904. Though the judge later expunged the entire examination, this man was asked if he had \u201cgiven considerable study to the Bible\u201d by Clarence Darrow. For the point, name this American politician and orator who died shortly after arguing in favor of Tennessee\u2019s Butler Act during the Scopes Monkey Trial.", "answer": "William Jennings<b> Bryan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After colliding with a truck driven by Robert Thompson, this man commented \u201cThis is a hell of a way to die.\u201d After the surrender of Japan, this man wrote \u201cYet another war has come to an end, and with it my usefulness to the world.\u201d During Operation Husky, this man participated in a race to Messina against Bernard Montgomery. While suffering from battle fatigue, Paul Bennett was slapped by this man. For the point, name this American general, known as Old Blood and Guts, who served under General Eisenhower during World War II.", "answer": "George Smith<b> Patton</b>, Jr", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This empire\u2019s history was detailed in a comprehensive historical encyclopedia called the<em> Suda</em>. One historian greatly exaggerated the atrocities committed by one ruler of this empire, claiming that \u201cten thousand times ten thousand times ten thousand\u201d people died during his reign. A female historian born to of a powerful ruler of this empire wrote about her father\u2019s reign in the<em> Alexiad</em>. For the point, name this empire written about by John Skylitzes, Anna Comnena, and Procopius, who wrote the<em> Secret History</em> about the reign of Justinian I.", "answer": "<b> Byzantine</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man claimed \u201cthere are extremists on both sides\u201d in response to an audience member\u2019s question at Ball State. Later that night, this man prepared his audience, asking people to lower campaign signs, as he began an impromptu speech from a flatbed truck in Indianapolis; in that speech, he noted that\u201cMartin Luther King dedicated his life to love and to justice between fellow human beings\u201d. For the point, name this former Attorney General who gave that speech after King\u2019s assassination, then was assassinated himself two months later by Sirhan Sirhan.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert Francis<b> Kennedy</b> (or<b> RFK</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This party devalued its nation\u2019s currency in 1994\u2019s \u201cDecember mistake,\u201d after which it plunged into debt paying off the<em> tesobonos</em> that were issued by this party\u2019s outgoing leader to raise support for the incoming Ernest Zedillo [zeh-dee-yoh]. Plutarco Calles [kai-yes] founded this party in the aftermath of\u00b4Alvaro Obreg\u00b4on\u2019s assassination. For the point, name this political party that, after seven decades in power through leaders like Carlos Salinas, was defeated by Vincente Fox\u2019s PAN in 2000\u2019s Mexican presidential election.", "answer": "<b> PRI</b> (or<b> Institutional Revolutionary</b> Party or Partido<b> Revolucionario Institucional</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The victor of this battle wrote two commemorations of it, known as the \u201cPoem\u201d and the \u201cBulletin.\u201dThe campaign leading up to this battle had been prompted by one side\u2019s capture of Amurru, and in its early stages, two Shashu spies informed the eventual winner that his enemy was encamped in Aleppo. The winner of this battle succeeded due to his composite bows and faster chariots, prompting the signing of the first recorded peace treaty. For the point, name this 1274 BC battle between Ramesses the Great and the Hittites.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Kadesh</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This event is referenced in the title of a speech that includes the poem \u201cThe Triumph of Freedom\u201dand claims that this event \u201creveals the gross injustice and cruelty\u201d of slavery. Frederick Douglass delivered that speech, asking \u201cWhat, to a Slave, is [this event]?\u201d On this day in 1826, a dying man lamented\u201cThomas Jefferson still survives,\u201d though Jefferson had actually died five hours earlier, on the fiftieth anniversary of the event that this holiday commemorates. For the point, name this American holiday, during which fireworks celebrate the nation\u2019s founding.", "answer": "<b> Fourth of July</b> (or<b> Independence Day</b>; accept<b> \u201dWhat, to a Slave, is the Fourth of July?\u201d</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Along with plums, these objects name a war that was ended by the Treaty of Teschen. Frederick the Great apocryphally ordered a field of these objects to be placed under armed guard which led to their prompt theft. Antoine-Augustine Parmentier helped to overturn laws outlawing the cultivation of these objects. Charles Trevelyan was accused of not doing enough to relieve a famine caused by the failure of this crop. For the point, name this tuber, whose destruction by blight caused an Irish famine.", "answer": "<b> potato</b>es", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The completion of this effort was marked by a nationwide message that simply said \u201cDONE.\u201d Asa Whitney and Theodore Judah were major advocates for this project, which was funded by the \u201cBig Four,\u201d including Leland Stanford. This project, which allowed for the creation of the popular \u201cOverland Route,\u201d relied heavily upon Chinese labor. For the point, name this project that was completed at Utah\u2019s Promontory Point with a golden spike.", "answer": "First<b> Transcontinental Railroad</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Milion, a monument inscribed with the distances to other cities, marked the beginning of this city\u2019s main street, the Mese. The Kentenarion Tower and Tower of Galata were two ends of a chain that defended this city\u2019s Golden Horn. The Tower of Galata was rebuilt in the Genoese district as a gift for Genoa\u2019s support against the Fourth Crusade, which sacked this city. In 1453, Mehmed II captured, for the point, what capital of the Eastern Roman Empire that was renamed Istanbul?", "answer": "<b> Constantinople</b> (accept<b> Byzantium</b>; accept<b> Istanbul</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}